ERIK DEMAINE: I think in the
very first lecture of class
we gave out a little survey.
Partly see what people's
background was, because this
is sort of a new class.
We didn't know exactly
how to position it
or where people
would be coming from.
So how much complexity
theory they knew
and how much
algorithms they knew.
And it more or less aligned
with our intent, which
was-- people knew some
algorithms and some of them
knew complexity theory.
Some of them didn't, and that's
what the class is aimed for.
You don't need to know a lot of
algorithms to take this class,
but definitely familiarity
with that kind of concept
is super helpful.
And then the other part
we were curious about
because we were still
designing the class--
and we designed it
throughout the semester
that I was teaching it--
was what topics were
more interesting than others.
And so we had some topics that
I was sure I wanted to cover,
because I knew them really well.
And I thought I had
a lot say about them,
and they're important.
And then there were a
bunch of other topics
where I was going to have to
learn the materials so I wanted
to some idea of which ones
I should learn more of.
I think the general response was
everything sounds interesting.
But there were a
few that stood out.
One of them for example,
was algorithmic game theory.
And a class called PPAD where
luckily my friend Costas
Daskalakis-- another
professor in computer science
here-- came in and gave
two guest lectures.
Really great, and they showed
everyone how this field worked.
And I learned a lot,
and we've done research
based on that since.
So there were a few topics
that stood out as particularly
interesting to the students.
And then one thing I was
particularly curious about
was the use of fun examples.
I was worried that
students would not
take the material seriously
if I only used fun examples.
But the feedback that I got
was that a lot of people said,
I want to see games and puzzles.
That's like among
the list of topics
everyone said, yeah,
more games and puzzles.
That's really fun.
They saw Mario in
the first lecture.
They're like, yeah
that was cool.
It was exciting.
So I took that as permission
to use a lot more fun examples.
And still there are some more
serious algorithmic problems.
But I think you can
get all the same--
you can understand
all the same material
and learn all the same
things through fun examples,
and just enjoy it more.
So the students--
I was very happy--
were aligned with
that view, and I
didn't have to worry
about students also
seeing tons of serious examples
in addition to the fun ones.
I used the survey to really
get to know the students.
And see where
they're coming from,
and help aim the
class in a direction
that they would get
the most out of it.