ERIK DEMAINE: I mean, I
was really happy with how
the class came out.
Even though I was learning
the material as I went
things came together
pretty well.
There are a couple
of the topics where,
because I was just learning
as I was teaching it,
I might have selected the
topics a little differently.
Now that I have a bigger
sense of the picture
I would maybe focus in on
some of the more interesting
subtopics within--
approximation algorithms
was one where it's such a
huge field it was hard for me
to learn all of it and then
pick out the best examples.
So I learned a big
part of it and then
picked out some examples.
But I would probably, now that
I have more experience with it,
I would do it a
little differently.
And, of course, there are more
topics that I didn't get to.
So next time I teach the class
I'll probably add in a few more
additional topics.
And kick out a few
others, which are still
available in video forms,
so they're not gone.