ERIK DEMAINE: So with every
sort of advanced class
that I teach there's
a final project.
And the goal of
the final project
is for students to
somehow get their feet
wet with the material
and sort of experience
it at a more researchy level.
In general, this can be
things like surveying papers
that I didn't cover in
the class because there's
only so much you can
fit in one semester.
So they'll go and read other
material and kind of aim
to teach that to the students.
So there's a written
project part,
and then there's also a
presentation in class.
So this is an opportunity
for students to learn more.
But actually most
students in this class
aim for a particular
type of project, which
is to solve an open problem.
So actually advance the
field and then present
their solution.
Now, of course, not
everyone succeeded.
And that's fine for a project.
You don't have to
solve the problem
that you set out to solve.
But at least you try
different approaches
and see what doesn't work.
But actually most students
actually solved their problem.
Often in groups.
So the group size is unlimited.
So sometimes 2, or
3, or maybe more,
I think maximum 4
students got together
and solved their
problem jointly and then
present their solution.
So I think, I mean it's
really exciting for me
to show that they
engaged with the material
so much they can actually
add new material.
But it's also, I think, really
exciting for the students
to show, hey, I can actually
solve these problems.
Many of the students were not
theoretical computer science
students.
This is not their
kind of main area.
But they were able to conquer
it anyway and have fun doing it.
So I think it's
a nice confidence
builder that actually--
you know, it sounds hard.
The field is called hardness.
But actually it's
pretty accessible.
And I think it gives
them the confidence
that they can go back
to their research fields
and say, hey, how can we prove
that our problems are hard.
And justify why we're
using heuristics
or why we're using
exhaustive search.
Maybe there's something better?
Actually, no.
We can show that's the limit.
We encouraged, for
all the projects,
not only to collaborate
with other students
but to collaborate
with us, the teaching
staff, the TAs, and myself.
So we would give them advice,
especially in the beginning.
So there's like a
project proposal stage,
we would confirm that,
to our knowledge,
this problem had not
been solved before.
And then we would give them
lots of pointers for, you know,
you might try this technique.
You should rewatch
lecture seven video
and see how those
techniques apply.
Or maybe you could reduce
from this or reduce from that.
Lots of different ideas for how
they might solve their problem.
And then some of them
came to us afterwards
like, well, I've gotten this
far but I'm stuck again.
Any ideas?
And so I think the
more you can talk
to people about where
you're stuck the less stuck
you will get.
And so that helped a lot,
I think people generally
found the solution.
Some people brought
their problems
to the open problem
session and had
all the students look at it.
So there were lots
of ways to do it.
But generally, collaboration
was the answer.
So the last part of the
project is for students
to present their work in class.
Usually it's a whole bunch
of student presentations,
one after the other.
So each presentation
is relatively short.
I forget if it was
like 10 or 15 minutes.
But I think it's really
valuable experience.
Presenting is also hard.
And the way to get good
at presenting your work
is to do it a lot.
And so, generally,
I find MIT students
are quite good at this.
They've had, I think,
a lot of experience
presenting their work.
But one of the things I
like to stress in my classes
is, because most of
the projects were
joint with multiple
students, how
to navigate a joint talk
where one person talks
for a few minutes or
one slide and then they
switch back and forth.
And I give general
advice about how
to do this but for the most
part the students just kind
of figure it out.
And by practicing they
find a good way to do it.
There are no videos of
the student presentations
because I think that would be
a little bit too intimidating.
It takes a lot of
practice before you're
comfortable being video recorded
like this and in your lectures.
But they are totally
of video quality,
so it's a shame we
can't share them.
But it's a chicken and
egg problem, I guess.
And so at the end of the
class the TAs and I each
write a bunch of bullet points
about their written project,
and the work that they did,
and their presentation.
And I pay particular
attention to like
how strong their
voice is, do they
have good presence,
and that kind of thing.
And try to give
them that feedback
so they know where
they need to improve,
or where they're
especially good,
or that the slides
needed more figures.
That's my number one comment.
Usually the answer is yes.
Can never hurt to
have more figures.
And also, on the
research side, we
think-- we look
at their results,
tell them whether
we found any bugs.
But for the most
part we're thinking
what would be the next step?
Like, oh, here's
another open problem
that would advance your
problem a little farther.
And here's some
ideas for solving it.
And that often leads to
papers that we publish.
And some final projects
are basically done.
Their papers are
ready to submit.
And then we give them feedback
on where they should submit it,
what would be a good
conference, a good journal,
we can basically
help them publish it.
So that's part of
the full service.