ERIK DEMAINE: Yeah, so
one of the exciting parts
of this class is that we ran
an optional session where
whoever is interested
in doing the research
side of the material could
solve open problems together.
So we call this a
problem-solving session.
But it's-- all the problems
are unsolved in the field.
And so it's not a required
part of the class,
because it's OK to just
learn the material.
But if you really want to engage
with what we're learning about,
then you should try
to advance the field
and solve new problems beyond
what we know how to solve.
And so every week I have
this session for two hours.
That seems to be
about the sweet spot.
And I would come with a couple
of new open problems inspired
by the material that
we've just covered
in the last week of lectures.
So this is, I find, a
really powerful combination
in teaching, where you've
just covered in one week
the latest that everyone knows.
Everyone's at the
state of the art.
They've just learned what the
best results are in the field.
And so it's natural to
ask, well, what's next?
What would be the next step?
How can we improve
these results?
What would be the
next thing to analyze?
And so the open
problem session nicely
dovetails with the
lectures, where
it's just been a
couple of lectures,
so it's still fresh in the mind.
And now we know all
these techniques,
can we conquer this new problem?
So the hardest part, of course,
as a teacher is picking out
what is the right
unsolved problem
to work on, because they have
to be easy enough that you have
the hope of solving them in
two hours, though, some of them
we continue through
multiple weeks.
But at least you want to make
some progress in two hours.
Otherwise, you feel like
you're wasting time,
and it's kind of discouraging.
But you also don't
want the problem
to be so easy that it's not
worth writing a paper about.
So the challenge is
to find this balance,
and also hoping
that the problem is
within the scope of the material
that you've just taught,
because it's unsolved.
No one knows whether these
techniques will apply.
But by bringing a few
problems to the table,
and also by the
end, students were
bringing in their own suggested
problems, you can get lucky.
And so in the
session, there were
about a dozen people typically
who'd show up each week.
It would shift a little bit
who has the time, because it
is kind of extracurricular.
But we would get together, I
would describe the problems
usually within
just a few minutes
and remind people of the
past problems from past weeks
and update.
If people had any progress
since the last week,
then they would present
what their ideas were
or what their things were.
But then most of the time
is spent brainstorming.
So often-- we were
in a room that
had lots of little
kind of corners, each
with white boards.
And so often, different
people would say, oh,
you want to work
on this problem?
And if so, come to
this little corner.
And then they would work in
that corner on their problem.
And so there would be
a few different groups,
each of like three or
four people brainstorming
about some problem,
maybe we could
do this, what if we applied
this technique that we just
learned from class,
and this sort of thing.
And then I would jump around
from corner to corner and try
to give my advice like,
oh, have you tried this?
Oh, this paper seems relevant,
maybe you should read this one.
And then in the span
of those two hours,
often, we would solve the
problems we would look at.
Certainly, not all of them.
But I would say maybe
half of the problems
that we set out to solve,
we actually did by the end.
Many of those turned
into the final projects
for students in the class,
so that was another motivator
for people to come.
And many of them have
been published since,
so they are now papers
in the literature.
And it's been a
nice way to progress
the field of hardness proofs.
And I think I think
this approach is really
powerful in general
for-- probably
for more advanced classes,
like advanced undergraduate
and graduate classes.
Anywhere people are comfortable
going that extra step
and trying out
research, I think,
this is a really
powerful technique
of combining teaching the
latest material in an area
and then trying to
push those frontiers
and solve new problems.
It takes extra effort, but
most professors are also
researchers in
addition to teachers,
so they should all try it.
And I'd be happy to give
them advice for how to do it.
I've been doing it
for several years
in all of my advanced classes.
And in the beginning
it was a little--
there are lots of kinks to
work out of figuring out what's
the right level of
problem, but now
it works pretty well
and pretty consistently.
I think one key to making
these problem sessions
work is you can't be
the only driving force.
You need to orchestrate
the students
to be willing to speak up.
I mean, it's always a
challenge in lectures to get
students to ask questions.
But this is like way
beyond asking questions,
now they have to like suggest
answers and suggest ideas.
And they have to be
in an environment
where they're comfortable
voicing their ideas
and not being too
self-critical, because when
you're solving problems,
it's really-- usually--
most ideas don't work.
That's life.
But silence is like the worst
thing for solving problems.
So even if you have like a kind
of lame idea, like you know
it doesn't work, it's
still worth saying it
because it might inspire
someone else to have
a second idea and a third idea.
And just keeping
the conversation
going is really critical.
So I think whatever
you can do to encourage
that kind of like--
including yourself, asking
silly questions that may not--
the answer doesn't really
tell you-- well,
what's the right way--
being comfortable not
knowing the answers
and asking initially stupid
questions that might lead
into interesting
directions, I think,
will encourage students
to do the same.
And it doesn't
work for everyone.
Some students remain quiet
throughout the whole semester.
But hopefully, they at least
got to see this picture
of how research happens.
That's sort of the goal.
The problem sessions
are definitely
much more personal
interaction with me,
and so they feel a lot
more comfortable around me
as the professor.
And so, yeah, they're definitely
more comfortable asking
questions in lecture.
It just generally leads to
a nice kind of-- I mean,
it's really a bonding
experience, I would say.
So I see it especially
within the group
that they're super comfortable
working with each other
because they've solved so
many problems together.
There's this camaraderie
of we can tackle anything.
And so this problem
session is continued way
past the end of semester.
It's been going for
another year since.
Hopefully, it will
continue going.
Of course, some students
will graduate and leave.
But it's actually been
great for my research.
If I have a new
hardness problem,
I can bring it to
the problem session,
and like wolves
they'll attack it.
And usually we'll get a
solution within a few weeks.
So it's really-- and a
big part of that, I think,
is because they've
shared this experience,
and they've solved so
many things together
that it really-- they have a lot
of confidence in this context.