ERIK DEMAINE: If a
student comes to me
and they're getting really
stuck in solving their problem,
then I would suggest to
them, collaborate more.
But I find
collaboration is really
the best way both to do
brainstorming because you get
very quick feedback
and ideas, but also you
get this kind of
compounding effect, where
your ideas inspire the maybe
more experienced person to have
some other idea, and oh, that
reminds me of this other paper.
Maybe you should
go look at this.
And so just talking with
people about your problem
makes a huge impact.
And maybe they join
in and help solve it,
or maybe they just
give one idea that
leads you down the right path.
But I think if you work by
yourself for a long period,
eventually you're
just going to get
stuck because it's hard to
maintain that kind of momentum
all by yourself.
But when you feed off the
energy of other people,
you can really go
much, much farther.
And it's also more
fun because you
get to be hanging out
while you're doing it.