ERIK DEMAINE: I
developed this class
on algorithmic lower bounds
because I felt like there
was no class like it.
And I really wanted to
share with the world
how to show that
problems are hard.
And in theoretical
computer science,
usually there's two kinds
of classes out there.
There's more
algorithmic classes,
which are about showing how
to solve problems and give
positive results.
Yes, this can be solved.
And there's another world
of complexity theory, which
is about building up a
mathematical infrastructure
to show that problems are hard.
But usually, it's
much more common
for the algorithms classes to
be tuned to particular problems
that people might care about.
And complexity theory is usually
more about theory building.
But there's this other world,
the hardness proof world,
which is much less common
and isn't usually represented
by a class, where
it's all about showing
that particular
problems you care about
are hard using the complexity
theory infrastructure that's
been built up.
So this class is very much
not a complexity theory class.
The goal is to
be-- because there
are lots of classes like that.
I wanted to use the complexity
theory infrastructure.
Just tell people what they
needed to know, but not show
how it works inside the
mathematical machinery.
Because it's quite complicated.
And instead, I wanted
to build on top of that
and show how to
prove equivalences
between different
problems and use
that to show that
your problem is
as hard as an other
known hard problem.
And that turns out
to be a lot of fun
and also very accessible.
And so my goal was to-- but
unless you're familiar with it,
it's quite difficult. My
goal was to make it easy.
The tagline is
"hardness made easy."
I wanted to bring
students to a point
where they're not scared to
prove problems are impossible.
It's actually not so
difficult. And it can be fun.