ERIK DEMAINE: I think fun
is a very important part
to life in general, and
in particular, work.
Maybe not so common
to view it that way,
but I think if you
have fun, if you enjoy,
and if you're passionate
about what you do,
then you'll do it well.
And you'll be super-productive.
And people will love you for it.
And so my guiding principle
in the research that I do
has been to always pursue
what I view as fun.
And sometimes it's things that
are very relatable as fun,
like games and puzzles.
Sometimes it's more
obscure things,
but I personally
find them really fun.
And maybe they're
more practical.
And so it's also nice
to have a mixture.
But in teaching, I think
learning should also be fun.
My dad raised me this way
when he was homeschooling me--
and that always,
you should learn
what you're curious about.
And so conversely
as a teacher, I
want to make material really
interesting and intriguing
and just fun to learn about,
because I think students will
be more excited and engage
more with the material
if they enjoy it.
Seems natural.
And so in this
class, I really tried
to bring lots of fun
examples-- I mean,
maybe there are some
more serious problems
that people have
proved hard, and then
there's more
entertaining problems
that people have proved hard.
So I often cover both.
But given the choice,
I would prefer
the one that's more
entertaining and something
that people can relate to, like,
yeah, I played that video game.
And it was really tough.
And now we can actually
prove that it's tough,
then that's what
makes it exciting.
And so it's really
nice-- I mean,
I view teaching as kind
a entertainment of sorts.
I think it's nice to
have that as a goal.
And if people are entertained,
they'll be engaged.
And they'll learn the material.
And they'll care
more deeply about it
and hopefully do research
in the field and all that.
When I was younger, when
I was a graduate student,
a lot of my more senior
colleagues, other professors,
would warn me that it was maybe
dangerous to pursue fun things,
that people would not
view it as serious.
And maybe you won't get
a job when you graduate.
And I kind of
ignored those people.
And it was a bit
of a bold guess.
But it worked out well for me.
And later, those same
people apologized
for making that suggestion.
I think, again, if you do
things you're passionate about,
you'll do them really well.
And you'll be very productive.
And so you can make up
for the topics being
more recreational by
showing that they're
really powerful and really
deep mathematically.
And that's turned
out to work for me.
Since being at MIT, it was,
again, like well, like, tenure.
Will people appreciate
the fun side of things?
And I do lots of serious
things in addition
to lots of fun things.
But it worked out.
I got tenure.
And in fact, I think it's an
important part of who I am.
One analogy is to
Martin Gardner.
He's sort of an idol of mine.
I never got to meet
him, although we
corresponded a little bit.
And he is called the father
of recreational mathematics.
He wrote a column for
Scientific American for decades.
And it really influenced a lot
of present day mathematicians
and computer scientists
to get into the field,
because they read this column.
And it's talking
about open problems,
but in a very accessible way.
He wasn't really
a mathematician.
He just learned
from mathematicians
that he knew and wrote about the
cool problems, very accessible
problems, and fun problems,
that people were working on
and what kind of
solutions they had.
And so Martin Gardner's
kind of a model--
although I do it more
in the teaching side
than in the writing
side-- of a way
to engage new people
into the field,
get people excited
about science,
and technology, and mathematics.
And I think MIT
appreciates that a lot,
that by working on fun problems,
you can reach a broad audience.
And when we proved Super
Mario Brothers as NP complete,
all the newspapers were
covering it, like, wow.
Hard Nintendo games
really are hard.
You know, mathematicians proved
this thing everyone knew.
It sounds funny, and so
it makes for good press.
And I think people are intrigued
by, oh, what does that mean?
Then they can go and read
the paper or take this class,
and it covers how do you
prove something like that?
And how do you
actually-- it's really
fun to prove that Super
Mario Brothers is hard.
You basically construct little
levels that build a computer.
So you build a Super
Mario Brothers level that
represents an entire computer.
And that's a fun thing to do.
And I think it can
get a lot of people
excited about computer science.
When I first came
to MIT, I used this
as a principle to get new
graduate students started.
So they're trying to
find a problem to solve.
They don't really know
what they're interested in.
So often, I'll suggest
a game or a puzzle.
Hey, let's prove this hard.
One of the first
ones was Tetris.
That was done with two MIT
students back in 2003, I think,
just after I started.
It's like, I've always
been curious about Tetris.
It seems really tricky.
And then together, we
proved that it was hard.
And that was their first paper.
And it got them kind
of psyched up and ready
to solve more problems.
They don't do hardness
of games anymore,
but it was like a nice warmup
to build their confidence
and show that they can do this.
So I think a lot
of these problems
are it's hard just made easy.
It becomes quite accessible.
One of the things that really
made me happy about this class
is-- I teach a lot of
advanced theory classes.
And each one of them has a
final project at the end.
And this class also
had a final project.
And there are many
types you can do.
But the type I'm always
most excited about
is to solve an open problem.
And in this hardness proof
class, most of the student
solved an open problem.
Compared to any other
class I've taught or seen,
many more students
solve the open problems,
because a lot of them are
relatively accessible.
You can take a game or puzzle
that just you like playing
and you have expertise
in, but no one else
has tried to analyze
mathematically.
And now, suddenly, you can
bring these new tools to it
and prove your result
and write a paper.
Fun is like the
hook that gets you
excited about the research,
the problems, and the material.
So we analyze a lot
of games and puzzles.
And most of them, to kind
of keep it interesting,
we analyze real world games
and puzzles, like video games
that people play.
And one example is
Super Mario Brothers,
where we can prove that it's NP
hard to figure out whether you
can solve a given level.
So there's no good algorithm
to, given a Super Mario Brothers
level, figure out
how to solve it.
This, I guess, becomes
particularly relevant
once you can make your
own custom levels.
So with the upcoming release
of Super Mario Maker, now
people can actually
build their own levels.
This'll be really fun from
a research perspective,
because we can take all the
levels that we've designed.
When we design them, we just
arrange them as pixel art,
so that you can see the
level, but you can't actually
experience the level.
And in order to actually
experience the level,
you'd have to modify
the ROM of the game.
And it's very tricky and
technically annoying,
and maybe also
illegal to do that.
Super Mario Maker suddenly
makes it accessible
that everyone can
make custom levels.
I think it also makes the
results more relevant.
It says, hey, if you
download a new level,
figuring out how to solve it is
going to be a real challenge.
And I think this
is a big reason why
people find video
games fun, because they
find them challenging.
I think if a game is too
easy-- there are exception
but if a game is too easy, it
gets boring pretty quickly.
And when there's
this nice-- when
you can set the
difficulty of the problem
so it's not impossible, but
at least it's a big challenge
to solve it, I think
that's where you get
the sweet spot in having fun.
And this whole area
of hardness proofs
gives you a mathematical way
of analyzing games and puzzles
to show, yeah, they
are really challenging.
They're hard even for
computers to solve them.
So for humans, it could be
also really challenging.