ERIK DEMAINE: I
mean, there's this
saying that the best way
to learn the material is
to try to teach it.
And that's definitely then
the case in this class.
I was learning every week,
learning a ton of material,
and then figuring out what
part of it I should actually
teach in a lecture.
And I think it's
valuable for the students
to get that kind of
experience, as well.
Where, just by trying to
write down the material that I
covered, they can think about
how would they present it
in written form, which
is a different style
of communications.
So it has different, sort of,
allowable structures and things
like that.
And just forcing them to
go through the exercise
of, how would I write
down this material?
We just saw it
presented one way,
maybe I'll write it
slightly differently,
or maybe I'll try to mimic
exactly how professor
Demaine did it.
Whatever their
approach, I think it's
valuable to go
through that exercise
and see what it's like to
write these things down.
And they scribe just one
or two lectures, usually
in a group of two
or three people.
So that gives them just a
flavor of what it's like.
Of course, another
useful product
is that we get these
lecture notes at the end.
So students can read
each other's notes
and have this kind of
reference material.
And good for OCW, as well.
So that everyone can read-- have
a written form of the lecture
if they don't like
the videos, or they
want to go through it
more quickly, or as
a supplement to
the videos, I think
it's also valuable for that.
One day this material
might turn into a textbook,
so it could also be a
step in that direction.
So there are lots of
reasons to do scribe notes
but I think mostly it's
as a useful experience
for the students to
actually do the writing,
see what that's like.
I guess it also helps
them learn the material
a little bit deeper.
Because by forcing them
to essentially teach it
in this written form they really
have to understand everything
that I said, and not just
kind of cursorily understand.
Follow up on the references
and things like that.
It's too much to ask everyone
to do that for all lecturers
but just to get a flavor of
that I think is valuable.
So writing is hard.
And I think the
only way to learn
to be really good at writing
is by lots of experience
and then lots of feedback on it.
So a lot of the
scribe notes that we
get in are poorly written.
And it's an area everyone
can always improve.
So we always-- we give feedback
on how to improve the writing,
mostly.
Occasionally there's
some missing parts,
like they forgot about one
section of the lecture.
And so say, hey, you've
got to add in this.
But mostly we're
aiming to improve.
Say, oh, we need a
figure here, this is not
clear just in written
form, or the grammar
needs improvement here,
or that kind of thing.
Or maybe you could
restructure it this way.
So we try to help students
learn the good ways to organize
their writing and
that kind of thing.
So it's certainly not the
main part of the class,
but it leads to much
better scribe notes,
and I think a more
valuable learning
experience for the writers.